nervous about it so yeah
so uh we got so I asked I asked Niels if
he wanted to be on the show and he said
uh sure Niels Niels uh Neil's Hof would
be happy to join you on your podcast uh
did I mention I'm HLF uh do you know
what Hof is I'm Hall of Fame I'm just
kidding Niels
nice opening line
[Laughter]
well tell us what how does it feel
it feels nice man I've had uh what is it
almost a week now to let it sink in and
uh
I said this at the other interview with
Mike uh for me you know I'm not all
about the pads on the back and all that
stuff it just doesn't uh
interests me that much but it's if you I
heard uh the count afterwards that there
was only out of 80 people in the Hall of
Fame there's only about 55 players in it
and if you think about that over the
last what is 120 150 years to be in
there that that for me is really cool
you know and it's a it's it for me it's
more about being in that group with with
my heroes like Efron Boosty Earl Archer
Ortman you know them from when I grew up
when I was watching those guys now I'm
in the same
uh yeah group I wouldn't say elite club
blah blah it's more that that that group
that's really cool I think for me
does that answer the question yeah yeah
I mean it's it's
I mean it's definitely it's definitely
not a uh I mean you look at the the
people that obviously we talked about
this a little bit uh a couple days ago
we did a show on who we voted for and
why uh Molina Mike Mike panoza and I
we're all three voters for the Hall of
Fame for full disclosure you got my vote
uh if you listen to that that podcast uh
you're actually the only person that I
voted for on uh the ballot this year and
I gave my reasons for it there so if
you're interested in why I voted for
nails and only Niels you could head over
there and you could you know listen to
why but uh
it is I mean at most you're basically
going to have one person in per year uh
there was one year where Johnny Archer
and Allison Fisher were both uh in you
know inducted into the Hall of Fame but
other than that it's been won every
single year
it's brutal to get into this uh I was
there for Rodney and Belinda one year
and uh I thought that was Harry Hearne
yeah so those those are meritorious
service so uh only one player can be
inducted at any unless they both get
over 75 so every every year every other
year they'll have a player up for the
meritorious service and then the year
that they don't have the meritorious
service they will have uh a Legends of
the a Legends category which is some
player who got overlooked while they
were on the ballot never got in and now
they're being looked back on 20 years
later and saying all right well this
person didn't get in but they're
deserving let's get them in now uh okay
so every every year they have one player
as as the greatest player category that
that I mean you could get in multiple
but it's got to be over 75 of the voting
um next year might be a potential year
for that uh obviously we all know Shane
has turned 40 this year it's possible
because you got Carlo beato guy young
Kim and uh Shane Van boning that are all
eligible next year
we've talked about that at length too as
to whether or not a multiple are going
to get in or whether or not you're going
to give Shane uh you know his his solo
year but then the following year you
might get carla'll be out on guy on
camera so we'll see uh but I guess back
to where we're at
it's really hard to get into this Hall
of Fame it's really really really
difficult it's you know looking back
over your career you've been playing
this game you're basically your entire
life right uh has it really totally sunk
in yet the players that you are a part
of now
uh yeah I mean I've been on the pro
scene let me think I got in I got really
into it since I was 20. then I did a
bunch of tours on in the US Road road
trips and then uh came back we were very
fortunate with the Dutch group that the
uh
uh uh Olympic Committee gave their stamp
on the on the Billiards Port right it
was eligible to be in the Olympics and
that meant that the Dutch Olympic
Committee gave a bonus to the players
when they got a medal at the Europeans
so I came back from three years touring
in the U.S six months on six months off
and we got a medal with the Dutch team
right away so that meant we got
financial support
uh uh so I could continue my Pro
situation right out of the gate coming
from the US and then in 2001 so this is
in what is this 99 2000 and then 2001 I
had my breakthrough year
with that Tokyo thing that was a big
check so I I had Financial Freedom very
quick uh so I could continue my my dream
and that's been going on for uh yeah 30
no is it 20 25 years on the on the
22 years as a pro I would say
22 23 years
yeah so to be like I said to be
part of my heroes in that club that's
that's the cool part for me and all the
rest is a nice big show but but uh
to get the the votes from your peers
uh um
to be I think that night will be cool
I'm curious how many of the the Green
Jackets will be there the former Hall of
Famers or the current Hall of Famers and
and how many of the old guys and and the
current Pros you know I think normally
they're quite good I think normally they
do like to turn up for these things I
think the majority of them will be there
if they are able to be there at the
international open as well as one of the
favorite events for the for them to come
you see you see a lot of the times on
the architect
um uh live stream you see
they get the they get the VIP area for
the whole experience and you see there's
quite a lot of them there all the time
so it's a I think it'll be a good night
I think you'll love uh you'll have
plenty of those guys to uh shake your
hand and you will get the Pats on the
back and welcome to the club
it could be quite an emotional evening I
think yeah it'd be a big build up I
think you know now it's uh it's like wow
nice but then you're gonna prepare and
I'm uh I'm Really Gonna push hard to get
the girls there that'd be a really nice
moment you know and uh of course it's
gonna it's gonna get build up like the
Moscone you know always before it's
gonna build and build
and then I think when I'm gonna jump on
stage and uh it's your whole body's
gonna be alive for sure yeah
and you've still got a tournament to try
and snap off at the same time yeah I
figured out it's the uh
from the Friday night it ends on the
Saturday I have no clue how how Pat's
running the event now I think it's now
single elimination I think that's a big
bummer in my humble opinion because I've
always thought the power of that event
was the double elimination till the
finals right so even if you had a bad
session on
Friday and you're uh you're jumping into
the losers bracket you can still come
all the way back and now it's single
elimination last 32 also
so anyway it's it's probably that
Saturday will be semi-finals finals so
the Friday night if you if you're not uh
still in you can have a couple of wines
more but if you're still playing yeah
you got I mean you're in the final four
so you got you still gotta get it yeah
get ready you said two times let me just
go through there's probably some missing
from here because I can't believe this
is the only
uh list or this is all that's on the
list but I guess these are the major
ones
so European Champion straight pool just
a couple of times
uh 2002 2003 2004 2007 2014 2017 2018.
nice of you to let somebody else win one
known again
European Champion eight ball 2000
you got third place at the world
championship 10 ball 2008.
world champion straight pool in 2008.
you got to the final two years in a row
in the eight ball 2010 2011.
winner of your first pool Masters 2013
nine ball world champion the big one
2014 and in another Whirlpool Masters in
2018 and then probably about another 100
events in between
I'd like to
just go back to 2018 probably 2017 into
2018. tough year you made it yeah you
made me think that you're never playing
pool again yeah this is going to be my
question I mean how close was it and how
close did you feel it might be to to
that elbow injury being the end of your
career
[Music]
uh I I didn't think it was gonna end my
career but the the toughest part of that
period was that no doctor or
uh in in Europe we call it a house
doctor right that's your local doctor
or uh
nobody was was giving me a number like
you're you're out for dude you're out
for six months you got a tennis elbow it
was like now I'll be two weeks more
it'll be another week another two weeks
so I was doing everything I could to try
and get like back on track ASAP because
they're after that summer there was a
whole uh list of tournaments for the
Moscone ranking we had terms in in uh
Germany and then uh whatever it was back
to back to back and I and I had to start
canceling events
so this was the start of it right that
was in August because I came back from a
vacation I drove back from Italy in two
days
and and that summer I already had some
some problems left and right I was I was
swinging uh Cena on the on the swing I
could feel like what's going on here and
then it would go away and then it would
come back and then it stuck for a while
I played the Euro tour in Holland and I
I couldn't shake somebody's hand it was
like oh man and I couldn't break the
balls really good it was really hurting
and then I said you know what I'm gonna
go to the physio
so I went to the physio here in my town
this guy tested me and says yeah you got
some problems with your elbow you got
you got to start lifting this weight
right do three kilos do it every day it
was way too much
and after three days my arm it just blew
up I went to the to the pool room here I
lifted my queue out to drop the cue
literally out of my hand
I was like what the hell so so the
inflammation got so intense that's when
I had to start taking a break
so that carried on and on I got really
anxious I was like what is and nobody
said it was a tennis elbow
so I'm doing everything I can blah blah
blah to make a long story short
I flew into Holland
had an appointment with a sports doctor
from the Olympic Committee he tested me
he says boom you got a tennis elbow
I said what a tennis elbow you're out
you're out this could be six to nine
months
I said man
and uh he said you got us open coming up
and you still have a chance for the
Moscone he said we could give you a
cortisol injection right that's what
they sometimes do and I was I was
anxious about that I said he said listen
it's not gonna it's gonna Not Gonna Hurt
blah blah it's not gonna hurt in the end
we did it I played the use open I played
the world championships with with heavy
painkillers because it started coming
back that's what happens
and then after the world's in December I
had to take the full break so now we're
carrying over winter 17 to 18.
and that's when I had to go into full
rehab for 10 weeks I couldn't play
winter dark here Scandinavia
and it was I was really depressing I
couldn't do any sports couldn't swim
couldn't bike then finally I could start
running and then I had to really build
myself up and just build new muscle I
had to build new
uh muscle tissue here around this this
this uh the spot where everything comes
together
so I was I was pretty depressed I didn't
think it was going to end my career but
I had
I had doubts about uh
just what was going on could I get the
same power back could I had the same
drive back
uh uh what would happen if I couldn't
continue you know you're just you're
thinking a lot if you have a big injury
anybody that has a big injury or had a
big injury you're thinking about it
you're thinking about it all the time
but my uh
especially if you've got nothing else to
take your mind off if you're not allowed
to do anything you can't take your mind
off it I didn't have anything to do I
couldn't work on like the the course or
or uh YouTube channel I couldn't I
couldn't be productive at all so I went
crazy if I can't be productive that's
just my personality I get I get really
irritated I got to do something every
day that's productive either work out or
something that makes me feel good and uh
so that was a really hard period but
then finally step by step you know I did
all the work and finally I got the green
light from the physio here
uh we made the movie about it with kamui
the great little three minute movie
and I mean I remember I was allowed to
break the balls for the first time
and it still hurt and I was like oh my
God man I gotta go to this tournament in
three days how am I gonna do this I was
allowed to play 10 minutes then 20
minutes 30 minutes
and uh I just went there and I just I
just was just glad to be there and then
I beat Raj you know Scrappy then I got
through Dennis I ran three and out but I
was still I wasn't really playing that
good but then
then I got pain-free in the semi-finals
against Carl and that's when all the
breaks just flew off right I've been at
I had pain for 10 weeks and when I got
pain free it was like I just shifted
gears like from second gear to 10th gear
I just didn't I just wanted to play I
didn't care about anything I was just a
little kid in the ballpark and uh I just
wanted to play
that's what you see in videos so if you
see those matches I'm just I'm just
just freewheeling I'm just running out
from Eric kicking balls in just running
out man that was that was the most fun I
had at the Masters ever I think those
two matches for sure
yeah long story but uh
it's never really been talked about I've
never really have the the feel we all
know what kind of what happened but you
know
um so I mean you you start off your
career in 2001 or you start decide that
this is what I want to do I want to be
professional then you you're very much
we hear it in your in the talks that you
give about goal setting setting yourself
goals and realistic goals and
how do your goals change throughout your
career when did you start thinking no I
think I can become a world champion I
know I want to be a world champion and
was there a point where you thought hold
on a minute if I look at this list
I might make Hall of Fame someday kind
of thing was that was there a moment in
your career where you thought about this
day happening but you thought this is a
possibility
uh yeah I think when you start racking
up some big results especially the world
title in 2014 then you start thinking
like I might have a chance for this but
it wasn't on my list or
I wasn't working towards it let's put it
that way I was just trying to win
tournaments and just play play better
and better and better
excuse me and um
I think the goal setting when you're
when you're a youngster in your early
20s I mean these guys now are 15 16. I
was like 22 23 I've been on the road you
know worked really hard on my game I
came back to Europe my goal was just
demolish everybody I just wanted to win
every freaking tournament you know the
cool thing I didn't think like okay I'm
gonna go on the Euro tour scene now and
I'm going to try and reach the final 16.
I said I want I want to jump straight
and winning Euro tour right so I got to
the finals then a year later second year
or so I got to the finals uh same year
tour and then the year after again in
Finland I won my first Euro tour
and uh
it was
for I felt like if you stayed in Europe
when I was early 20s it went too slow
that's why I went to the US and in the
US I got so inspired man I'm around
these Champions all the time I'm on the
road so I came back to Europe
and at that time I just didn't fear
anybody I was like dude I've been
through all of this
that was my mindset do you think I fear
any of this coming back you know what I
mean so I just wanted to jump in fresh
and uh then of course when you turn pro
you're gonna play more events and you
start figuring out that other guys are
can also play really good tournament
pool
a little harder you know and then it's
one
you're observe it's a whole other animal
to win a world title that's uh
Pro pool at the highest level is more
about pressure management and momentum
carrying that confidence momentum over
and and you know and capitalizing on
that like look at Sanchez it's like that
streak that's that you see that with
you've seen that with Mika and Darren
and myself and Sanchez
uh Ralph it's usually that streak when
you get confident really confident you
can carry it on for a while
um
so yeah just gradually setting setting
higher targets and then uh
eventually you see a whole list of nice
things you think this yeah this might
work for the Hall of Fame why not
okay so you've sent all these targets
and you you've met them all I mean
there's nothing that you that you
haven't achieved it was open okay it's
almost good to see it yeah what is what
what is know your target I mean you know
46 years old with Hall of Fame a world
champion okay you could name the US Open
as being a Target because you don't have
one of them but how do you keep setting
yourself targets when you've achieved
almost everything
well I'm not I'm not delusional you know
my life right now doesn't look like my
not my life in my 20s and 30s without
kids uh without without uh
other responsibilities commitments uh I
have to really work harder to uh get in
stroke stay in stroke you know when
you're
when you don't have all those
commitments so that's all you do you're
playing pool you're always in stroke and
um
that's the thing I struggle with the
most nowadays is you know if I if I
would
want to Peak more I would have to play
more events but I don't want to do that
because I also want to see my girls
so sometimes you think it takes me
longer at events sometimes to get in
gear like mentally tough getting
adjusted that takes a little longer and
that's sometimes frustrating because you
think like man if I
would have only played these two events
before I would have had a you know what
I mean but that's that's a trap you have
to stay away from
um so the goal for me is still to win a
major I think personally in my heart
that I play better now I'm more complete
than when I won the world title I think
I'm more fit than in my 20s and 30s
uh so energy wise uh fundamentally wise
like my lifestyle and stuff as a pro and
game wise I think I still can do it I
got to the quarters at the at the worlds
I had Mario 9-6 and he ran the setup
from nine eight otherwise I'm in the
semis perhaps against Sanchez you know
I'm at least third then so then I got
third at the Masters lost Hill little
Kachi that was that was a nice one so
it's still there it's just uh
it's it's a little harder with you know
playing out there's so many events I
gotta just pick them I can't play
everything instead you know that that
would not be my my life wish
at the moment so that's sometimes
internally a struggle
but uh
also I can let go of that pretty quick
because I I'm uh I'm rich on the home
front so to speak I have I have a nice
I have nice girls that sometimes drive
me absolutely crazy but I'm there tell
me about it I'm there you know I mean
I'm in the arena with that also so so
you you talked uh you talked a little
bit about the mental side now I do want
to get to that in a second but I want to
touch first off about uh you said
um you wish you would play more events
but you know all things considered how
do you actually pick your schedule do
you just look at the matchroom schedule
and say all right this is mine do you
look at the Predator schedule I mean how
are you actually looking through
everything that's available and saying
these are the ones I want to throw my
hat in the ring on yeah good question I
mean uh well if you look now uh it's
kind of summertime so I said okay I'm
taking three weeks off even if there's a
Euro tour next week I say okay three
weeks off we're going on a little trip
here on Saturday a week
and then once I'm back you look at the
calendar and then you see okay there's
tournament in Sarajevo connected to the
European open so I could say okay I'm
going straight to the European open but
then I have that problem again I don't
really have that
competitive Groove so I'd say okay I'm
going to Sarajevo and straight after to
Fulda so I hope to get like at least
five to ten matches in Sarajevo to get
me a little sharper
uh then there's a little break again uh
but September is going to be busy with
I'm going to again ball Contour
straight to Jason's tournament
Connecticut and then on to the U.S open
so that's a nice little block
um and then we're is that September yeah
and I'm doing the pros yeah that's end
of September yeah I'm doing the pro star
before that so there was a uh a problem
there because China open came up now
China open I got the invite but that's
you know that's again I have to choose
if if I would do that also it would be a
week a week a week
a bit too much so my heart would say
yeah China open nice but
no I'm doing Pro Stock up with my whole
family we're going to the camping there
staying for a week so it's practice
tournament little uh vacation all
together quality time and a tournament
so I try to do these mini blocks
throughout the calendar and uh you know
if you're if you're now a youngster a
touring Pro you would just go left and
right you know what I mean you would go
from China to
to there to the European open to the US
three weeks four weeks go to uh the
Philippines what's up Asian open you
know what I mean
but I guess again I guess in a way
because there are so many tournaments
now to pick from you can make your
schedule based on what you want to do
rather than being free in between the
tournaments the only tournaments that
you have to play you know if there's
only one tournament every month then
your free time is decided by when the
tournaments are whereas now there's so
many tournaments that you can turn
around and say I'm taking this three
weeks off because it's the school
holidays I'm going to go to Tom with the
family and you know there's a tournament
before you stop and there's a tournament
yeah when you come back because even
there's just a tournament every week now
potentially then you could go and play
you know
so you're never you're never going to go
dry I think anyone if you want to be one
of those young kids who just plays
absolutely everything then you know you
live and have a suitcase for 365 days of
the year and you're only traveling or
you can just choose to pick and choose
the the ones that you want and
I think most I think most people they're
they're probably Nate asking you know
what how do you pick your tournaments I
think the majority of people their
priority at the moment goes towards the
nine ball ranking kind of thing that
seems to be the the the the way the most
are doing it if they have to pick and
choose but
I I like the way that you always go to
your you you always uh go to like the
the pro star and the longoni tournaments
uh you've got a very tight bond with
longone I mean I can't believe that in
all the time that you've that no other Q
manufacturers have been trying to head
hunt you and get you to move but you've
obviously loyal to longoni kind of thing
you like a sponge you like a sponsor's
dream you don't go chasing them yeah no
you see players of switching queues
every couple of years have been get
offered about contract you're always
very loyal at your sponsors is that
something you're that
you're very deliberate in making sure
that if somebody is going to support you
that you do the best that you possibly
can for them and support their events
and all that kind of stuff
I think uh it's it's a really good
relationship with Pierre Luigi you know
I've been with him since I think it's
2003 or four
um and uh they're just really good
people so you know every time we see him
or we go out for dinner and we we catch
up about the scene and about new
possibilities with products and new
developments and uh he's just a really
really good guy
uh and of course we have to talk
Financial stuff also but that's never
been an issue or a debate or anything
it's uh it's just a really nice family
feeling
and also you can you can say okay I'm
gonna go to this Cube brand for three
years and then who knows they might drop
you and what do you have then you know
what I mean I've been with longone for
20 years and uh we've never had any
issues whatsoever if there was anything
that came up it was boom pick up the
phone and 15 minutes later we spoke
things out which there was hardly ever
anything anyway so uh
you know even if I get 33rd at a
tournament doesn't even matter you know
or if I win it's great but it's more the
long the longevity of it and and The
Branding they believe more in The
Branding in the long term
uh
so that's they always have my back and
that's a really uh a really cool thing
that's that's nice you don't have to
worry about oh I have to get to the
finals in this tournament or I might
lose my Q sponsor or anything
it's never never been an issue and he I
think he's always valued my uh ethics as
a pro uh connected to his brand so
that's that's a win-win seems very
difficult not to yeah
like a sponsor's dream I mean even even
for the podcast you've obviously gone
and Put Your sponsorship shirt on for
the for the podcast I'm pretty sure you
didn't go out for dinner wearing that so
yeah
you can go back and got changed to make
sure you guys but yeah but not everybody
you could laugh but not everybody does
that you know this you know this yeah
it's one of the things we talked about
when we talked about how do you how do
you rate somebody for being in the Hall
of Fame you know do you do it just based
on results but it's a full package you
know and
um we we talked a little bit about the
the youth coming through before we came
on here and stuff like that and what the
youth really need is they need they they
need ambassadors of the sport they need
people to look up to they need people
that they say I want to be like that
person you know that's why I like I mean
I like I like you as a pick for Hall of
Fame on a personal basis anyway because
we're friends but also I think it's just
a great pick because of the the full
package you kind of tick all the boxes
in my opinion and when kids are coming
through they need to be able to see role
models and say this is who I like to be
like in order for that to happen we have
to reward the people who are
yes and are the role models so that they
used to see these people this this guy
is getting rewarded for everything he's
done in the beginning and he's doing
this he's he keeps himself he's always
well dressed
he looks after he sponsors and he
sponsors look after him he's always very
professional he's respectful everybody
has respect for him these are the kind
of guys that are Role Models but you
have to push them forward and say we're
rewarding somebody for being like that
and not just ignoring somebody when
they're like that you know what I mean
and
I think it's uh
no I'm I'm I'm I'm delighted on this one
because we all know that if you hadn't
gone this year you would have to wait
another year anyway because next year is
which already decided
that it happened this year
um and uh I think it's I I for all you
kids out there that are looking if
you're looking for somebody to to model
your your game on or your behavior on
well uh uh back back way early on the
podcast when I first started doing this
I used to bring on one player every week
uh back when I actually I guess had more
time to do this but uh I bring on one
player every single week and we would do
player profiles on them and we would ask
basically the same questions over and
over and over again so that we got a
little bit better idea on the players
and one of the questions that I asked
was who is who is your role model in
pool uh you know for all the players
over let's say 40 that I brought on at
the time uh it was a buddy hall it was
Mike Siegel it was those types of
players I'm not kidding you every single
player under the age of 25 your name
came out of their mouth whether you are
the or whether you were amongst two or
three well every single player over I
probably did I mean they're still out
there I probably did
maybe 10 to 15 interviews of players
under the age of 25 and every single one
of them mentioned your name well you and
you and Ralph were a you and Ralph you
were the number one Ralph was number two
as far as who they respected the most
growing up playing so yeah I'm a little
fitter than real no I'm just kidding
you're a little younger as well
that's uh that's crazy that's crazy
even even when even when you talk to the
current pros and you and
you know you're getting the
conversations of you know
the the the the most professional the
hardest working you know the the the
best attitude
Neil's name I'll say it again if your
name's in the discussion you're doing
something right and Neil's name is
always in there even with the top guys
when I speak to Darren to Jason you know
they all they all come out with the same
names and wheels is always one of them
you know and uh
is just like putting the cherry on the
top and it's a legacy you know you're
now you're now
Eternal you know you're
your name will always be there no you
know and and deserve it Hof
you get the Green Jacket yeah yeah I did
the measurements yesterday because I
heard a story or was it yesterday
Ralph supposedly uh did the measurements
and it let's say he's a 48 or a 50 but
it's totally different in the US so it's
like minus 10 something like that so it
should have been a 38 for him in the U.S
so he gets his jacket and it's a U.S 48.
they said like make sure you get the US
size so I'm a 52 I put straight into the
conversion and it was like a 42 so I
send it over to Shane I'm just imagining
Ralph up there just going like this with
his arms yeah yeah yeah he wouldn't like
that the little flaps are just going all
over the place
you've got to come up with a speech now
yeah not to go too deep into it but it
must already be in your head is there
any any names that come to mind straight
away that have had um
influence in your career
as oldest but uh
talk to me uh
no I think top five I mean uh you have
Johan uh you have uh Stephen fahana from
eight five you know he used to drive me
to all these tournaments in Holland when
I was 17 18 we always go together
from eight five then you have Alex
grunerwald from eight five who got me in
contact with Joker when I was 20 that
was my first Contact in the in the US so
that's then yolang also uh spoke with my
parents when I was 17 tried to convince
them more to push me to to keep playing
uh then he was out of it for a long time
yo and he wasn't involved with pool and
then he came back he was of course the
Dutch coach Moscone coach so I uh I
worked with yellow one for many years
and then uh Aaron zentley
uh Corey dual stay course he's take me
uh when I was 21 22. friend of mine you
know he let me always play better
players he always put me in the Box
against better players take me because
that's how he believed that would get
better
and then uh
I'm probably forgetting uh you know I
gotta make a list like top five to go on
but there's so many guys man it's unreal
but my wife I mean top of this problem
with my wife you know because also if
you get the jet lags you know it's not
it's not easy to be with a pool player
and it's uh
uh she is a pool play she used to be a
pool player I'm trying to get her back
on track she it's not gonna happen but
cat got a silver medal herself with the
Europeans and a bronze medal years ago
so that's how we met at the Europeans in
um so she knows the game in and out and
we travel together but you know when the
pool player is jet lagged and he comes
home from a trip and he mentally
destroyed uh it's not it's not always
happy days you know uh you can have a
little uh your squibbles and your this
and that but uh
at the end of the day I mean she's she's
the foundation for for everything in
this house if
you know I mean uh I can I can thank uh
20 guys but she's she's always there
when uh
when I'm down or or or stuff you know so
yeah it does take a special kind of lady
to be in a relationship with a pool
player at any level I mean even even the
good ones
and think about think about the pool I
mean we don't make millions right so
it's there's there's a lot of pressure
on pool players right you got to go out
and you got to keep going out and try to
make a living and there's uh there's
been many divorces in the pool world
there's not a whole lot of a lot of guys
that are are on tour with with two kids
and that have a marriage I mean it's
very two success stories
none with two kids with the same woman
that they're still married to
five six kids
you know for our world if you if you
golf players and you make uh a million a
tournament you you bring everybody on
the road or like fate or you know I read
his latest book uh the master or
whatever he brought a private jet and he
had two twins and he brought nannies and
teachers and private houses I mean who
did you just say Federer Roger Federer
Oh I thought you said Fetter I'm like
yeah
if he's got it man he needs to get
banned from uh events more often if he's
he's having that kind of success
he just went on Facebook earlier today's
sporting two new Rolexes that he's just
got so he's doing okay I think
so uh all right uh I want to ask a
couple of like uh lightning questions
you know just quick questions that uh
questions you wanted to talk mental you
said right well do you want to do that
first whatever you know let's let's do
let's do the mental side of this because
uh okay so obviously like let's put this
disclaimer out there I'm nowhere close
to the the player that you have ever
been but
um as I as my pool career slows down I I
find that the hardest part that I deal
with is the mental side of things and
it's not the mental side of things of
um
like being ready for an event it it's
it's maintaining the Readiness
throughout the event whether you're down
five to zero up five to zero or you know
just you know you you get down with a
really intense hill hill match and you
know you go sit at the bar and have a
water or a soda or something like that
and you know you're just kind of coming
down from it and all of a sudden you get
called to the next table uh and you got
to go up and down and up and down and
while when you're playing a lot that
stuff's pretty easy to do right it's
just it's just ingrained into your your
uh your your competitive abilities but
when you're not playing a lot and you
pick up your cues once a month or once
every other month or you know whatever
it is to be able to get into that uh
mode stay in that mode and more
importantly come down from it and get
back up into it Without Really catching
a you know without really losing
anything that's really hard to do I've
really struggled with that
I would say it sounds a little bit like
that's kind of where you're at where
you're you're um you're playing these
World quality events and then you're
going and having a holiday with the wife
and kids and then three days later
you're home and then you're back at your
your next event playing for you know
your career it I guess just talk a
little bit about that and then maybe you
can transition that into into the actual
uh course that you've created to help
players with stuff like this
oh
um
yeah I think if you're if you're
competing right and you're trying to
you're trying to stretch yourself
so I mean there's nothing wrong with
playing for fun and having having a
drink and your league nights and all
that stuff that's that's fine that's fun
uh keep that up but if you're trying to
push the envelope if you're trying to
get better
that means you got to step out of your
out of your comfort zone right and if
you're going to do that but by
definition you're going to feel
uncomfortable a lot of times
and that's when you're really starting
to learn things about yourself and you
have to
search for answers and you have to you
need help I mean I've done it took me 30
years to build a whole package from from
uh Hard Knocks and reading books and
talking to people and working on myself
and and one-on-one sessions and sports
psychologists therapists you know just I
wanted to work on myself like why is
this thing blocking me and why is why am
I struggling with this and what's going
on with that and
uh finding answers you know what I mean
and then you put that to work
so
to answer two questions for myself I
know if I want to get competitively
tough to compete in the arena with the
best I gotta go out there and compete
with good players it's not going to help
me to just be out here by myself you
know I can run 150 balls no problem
because there's no heat uh there's no uh
I'm all by myself just chilling out
practicing
uh but then if you go let's say into a
pool room and uh and there's ten a pro
sitting around your table because you're
playing 500 a set against another Pro
that's a different kind of heat or if
you're stepping into a big arena playing
uh Center Court in front of the lights
the only thing you can do is go out
there and do it you know and you got to
do it often you got to do it frequently
so it's a much overlooked thing is I'm
gonna do a video about this one day
YouTube video is building these streaks
of events it's very hard to get used to
pressure if you're doing one event
three weeks later one event two weeks
later one event it's better to do like a
block like three four events and then
once you hit that second third fourth
event it's like your living room because
you're doing it and doing it you're
stress your nervous system gets used to
it
Etc that's one part of it now what do
you do when you're actually in the event
that then it comes down to uh what's in
the in the mental courses one part match
preparation like what do you need for
your personality to get ready for your
match a lot of people don't even know
what they need they don't even know what
the hell their ready looks like they
chit chat with everybody where actually
they need like five minutes by
themselves outside just getting cleared
out and then go back in and Hammer it
other people need that time to chit chat
they need that nerves energy out right
like uh like Rodney used to do in Earl
then Raj they needed to talk to a lot of
people and get it out and that's what
worked for them I I'm not like that I
need quiet me time before before a match
earpods in I gotta build my focus up and
up and up
um so that's one part of and then part
two is your mental Foundation uh during
the event like away from the matches
when you're home meditating uh uh
visualizing perhaps creating mental
space whatever works for you you need to
be able to focus if you're always
cluttered up and you're and you're not
even able to focus or if you're sleeping
five hours a night and you get no energy
well good luck the next day having a
good practice session or a match there's
no way you know what I mean these mental
Foundation things like inside knowledge
and then during the match uh it can be
uh
well what the heck the rest you have to
pay for the rest of it yes yeah so
that's your free sample uh yeah
[Laughter]
well that's fine we I'm assuming I don't
know maybe I
well you could stick up he's a if you
want to know more while we're trying to
get meals back if you want to know more
about what Niels is talking about you
can go to the Terminator College just
type it out near College it'll all pop
up Meals is this expansive course he'll
do 30 minutes with you uh face to face
uh over the over Skype or Whatsapp or
whatever he'll talk to you and find out
exactly what you need he was talking
about it there find out what you need
yourself know yourself a little bit
he'll figure that out for you and you
can go through the whole uh course and
the course is basically valid for as
long as you want it to be valid for you
keep returning to it uh to pick up tips
and um
he spent a lot of hard working at that
and uh I've only heard good things from
the people who have who have gone into
it so it's worth taking a look at the
Terminator college and have a look at it
yeah I put it into the comments so if
you want to see it uh
I know we brought him on to uh actually
I think right after he uh he finished us
up we brought him onto the podcast to
chat it out and so that we do have a
podcasted there too if you want to know
a little bit more about the specifics of
it
are we back
testing
yeah we got you
I can't see you because
testing can you hear us
yeah I can hear you guys can you hear me
yeah we can hear you we just couldn't
see you because you need to pick up this
massive big Terminator College banner
over there
I lost connection a little bit I had
some struggles here I apologize
so where was I meant uh mental match
play that's uh all about handling tilt
expectations frustration anger
all this stuff like uh Insight talking
to yourself breathing exercises
that's really powerful and then after
the match where a lot of people struggle
is they perhaps they're really hard on
themselves and they go into a slump
right uh this didn't go well
I should have done this I suck blah blah
and I have a whole schedule of uh
feedback loop that you can go through
can take you maybe five minutes ten
minutes to keep you positively charged
for the next event like what went well
what needs work what are you going to do
to fix it instead of this
I saw I should have done that uh I'm not
playing well blah blah blah
and then there's a book list quick learn
guides and then you get 30 minutes of
Skype with me that's all in the big
course so that I mean that was really
cool to make that's standing there over
2500 people have joined to college
uh so that's that's really cool so yeah
that's really cool
so that's that's insane 2500
yeah
oh man come on now
you're good it's Nate that's frozen I
said oh man not again
I'm getting nervous
yeah am I Frozen
no you're good oh okay yeah you put you
put meals on tilt yeah
back to the breathing yeah and I will uh
on Facebook I will pin the link to
terminatorcollege.com it's just
terminator.college.com so uh if you want
to check that out that's that's where
you can get that for um
yeah I guess is there anything else you
want to discuss with that I mean there's
how much content is on there like if you
were to go through all of the content uh
how long do you think it would take you
to to just go through everything
couple hours it's 33 videos
uh I mean that depends on you if you
wanna if you want to order some books
not mine but like uh really top books
and uh then you get the 30 minutes you
know so everybody runs into situations
where they think oh man this is just
what I'm struggling with and then we can
dive in a little deeper you know I can
maybe recommend some other books or some
other tips for you personally
that's really cool I've met a lot of
nice
really wonderful people in in chats and
you know you open that screen on Skype
or whatever you've never met this person
but you you're on the same
path like you know I feel what they feel
and and uh you're not that much
different because you all share the same
nerves and and you know pressure and
passion and all that stuff so it's
really cool to uh to be able to help
people from all different ages and uh
it's cool right now I'm doing 30
discount because of the Hall of Fame so
just go to the college and then check
out page it's Fame 30 in big letters you
get 30 off so this is just just be clear
this is this is for all levels of
players it doesn't matter what kind of
level you're at it will work for
everybody yeah it doesn't matter yeah
exactly
and Fred Dinsmore says uh it works
perfect
wow
he's got some mental issues so if he
says it must be pretty powerful stuff
we're all working yeah
yeah
okay this one I got one more question
now that you're you're 46 year old and
you've built up all this this this
massive amount of information that you
have through your years of experience
and and doing all your mental stuff and
everything
so let's say you had the opportunity of
the 46 year old needs fine going back
to talk to the 22 year old Niels fine
well you get five minutes with him what
are you gonna you know what's the kind
of things you're gonna be saying to him
um
I would
say one thing and that is
play one pocket
when I was because I went to the states
and I never properly got introduced to
the full power of one pocket when I was
20 man it was so boring it was just
tapping balls and then now like 10 years
ago you got this DVD from Scott Frost
like power one pocket man it's like dude
if I would have seen this when I was 20
you know I would have been hooked and it
would have given me so much
uh tactical game when I was younger you
know we were we were figuring out
everything by ourselves at in that
generation the break
kicking we were you know now it's all on
YouTube we were trying to figure it
figure it out with with Alex laylee and
Nick and me and Rico and how would we do
this how should we do that in the drill
for this and you know these guys they
knock off 10 years of their learning
curve these youngsters just because it's
all online
so I would definitely say
work on your tactical side ASAP because
I was just the run out uh uh addict I
just want to run out of run racks uh
that's why one on the spot with a normal
rack still my favorite because that's
where I ran 15 racks in a row
and and straight pool you know just get
the run out run out
um
but yeah I think besides that I wouldn't
my work ethics and and all that stuff
was really high already then so I would
just say just just keep keep hammering
just do the same thing
you know and then eventually the life
lessons will will will follow but for
pool the Tactical side ASAP especially
for for
the youngsters
I can't believe you said one pocket I've
just got this vision of Molina Mike
dancing around his living room Neil said
Tower one pocket
yeah right
all right Niels you ready for a couple
uh rapid questions let's do it
all right
what was your most accomplished win
everything taken into consideration the
2014 World title
all right uh you never win a single
event the rest of your career but you
can trade that for a US Open title
which do you take
no do you take it no no way
for you mean everything I've won now put
that away
from here going forward so you will not
win another event for the rest of your
career but you'll win this year's US
Open do it yep happy man
[Laughter]
uh what is so if you could win three or
what are the what are three more events
that you want to win by the end of your
career obviously the US Open being one
of them
uh uh
three I mean
US Open
I would say one I mean if if I would
like to win another European straight
pool just for personal reasons just
because I uh I just have something with
that event really I started to make my
goal to try and win 10. I've got seven I
got close last year 27 wins and that
isn't enough
no
it's not a massive it's not a massive
gold it's just for personal Pride
because last year I ran four times 100
in that event I had three hundreds in a
row
and I just felt I was I was the best
14-1 player in that room and I wanted to
win you know what I mean that's how you
have to feel as a pro otherwise you
cannot beat these guys so uh that's just
personal
another I would just uh
I think another you know these are
massive goals another world title I
really had a strong desire to this
winter to win that world title because
it it came like right after the
Christmas period right a little break
couple of weeks off and I it just man it
just I would just felt it you know I
wanted to put everything into winning
that thing we had Dutch championships
then straight to Taiwan the boot camp
and then straight to the world title you
know I put every effort into it to get a
good result I really wanted to win I I
did as good as I could you know I played
good
good preparation so that would be of
course a massive win so I hope that
answers it
yeah perfect uh
who was your favorite person to play
against in your entire career
like who who was it you saw on the
bracket you get to play them and you
just got excited for it maybe because
you had a good record against somebody
just because you like competing against
that one person but who looking back at
your career who was the one person that
you enjoyed playing
one guy
or if or or a few
yeah there's a couple of there's
multiple reasons there was uh Efren
because he was uh I mean it was the
greatest that you know the elite of the
elite in my 20s I saw him Deuce just
stuffed some believe but we've all heard
those stories so it was the inspiration
and then get the play and was just the
focus was just boom and uh I always
I always for some reason I always played
good against Archer I just had matches
with him where I just played like
unbelievable and uh you know I I have
really good respect for Johnny
I think he's really nice and and really
cool Champion uh also in the Moscone
I've always had nice chats with him
so I I enjoyed playing him we had really
cool battles also Hill at the U.S opens
and uh there's other guys but that's
that's personal reasons that's more um
rivalry stuff and uh not gonna seems
like a perfect platform for us
uh respect for The Other Guys
is there anybody
on the other side of it is there anybody
that you didn't like playing against for
any sort of reasons
yeah I think uh to be honest I never
like to play the
the guys that manipulated the rack like
I had no problem with with a little bit
of pattern racking you could you could
talk about that and get it out of the
way
but to cheat on the rack and really
leave gaps and uh
I just felt it's so nice to hear the
professional actually call it cheating
well I mean and I completely agree it's
cheating
but Jim I ride my bike the Tour de
France is going right I followed by
cycling for years and for me it's doping
it's mechanical doping EPO doping all
together in one thing I think there's
and I'm gonna say to Salah and I'm not
ashamed I think there's people that want
U.S opens
by doping and I'm going to say that I
don't I don't care and uh
I mean there's a couple of guys there's
a handful of guys that have that have
manipulated that and if you're in the in
the Pro field and you're not doing the
same thing you have zero chance like at
events like Derby back then
U.S opens you go it's like getting
it's like them getting four to five
racks on The Wire yeah uh by by opening
up those gaps behind the back balls
where the corner balls just keeps flying
in and flying in you just get no chance
if you're not doing the same thing
eventually you're gonna they're gonna
catch you and you're gonna lose
so I've had I've had multiple I mean
I've had huge discussions uh about the
wreck and also in the accusted arena and
and to be frank people just didn't
understand it they had no clue what was
going on they thought uh why why are you
whining about the rack it's don't you
understand if I don't do this I have
zero chance this guy has to close these
balls if we're playing like even with
the with the normal rack there were you
know they're doing stuff and opening up
that back ball or pushing out the wing
ball
it's doping it's pure doping in my
opinion and I think they they should
have been barred or at least be
disqualified out out of the room and uh
uh Bart for a year come back next year
that's why I was so glad that they
finally started implementing neutral
records at these events they started at
uh that was it still the US Open back
then I think it was
flaming's tournament there's I think it
was still Barry Berman's then they
started with neutral records I was a big
vote for that and uh I that that really
helped to clean up that side of the
sport because I'm at it was just a joke
it was it was I get it I get angry about
it you could tell but it was like if
you're a young pro and you go join that
that tour and at first you're gonna get
hammered and you don't know what's going
on and then you see okay uh
I see what they're doing now do I want
to do this or do I want to work at the
supermarket basically
right you love the game you want that's
the same in cycling these kids were 20
years old what are you going to do take
the injection or go back home well yeah
that was a lot of people's uh that was a
lot of people's you guys don't like
baseball that much in Europe but I mean
that was the big argument during the
steroid era of baseball when people are
hitting 50 60 70 home runs a year it's
like well I know that I have to take
steroids because I know the picture
that's going to be throwing this ball at
me is taking them and do I do I really
want to give them
you know that that extra you know little
10 20 on top of them yeah it's
so how
well I mean we're not we won't ask you
for actual names but how many during
this era that you're talking about how
many of how many of the players how many
of your contemporaries do you think
we're doing this manipulating the racks
in this way good question I know I know
for sure five guys but it might have
been a lot more uh
uh I don't I don't know if I mean like I
said pattern racking you know you can
get you can have a big discussion then
it's out of the way you know then you
just rack them like you do now and the
two is random or whatever
but to like start tilting the rack and
lowering the rack and opening up balls I
mean then you're really coming into a
great dark area I think uh
and unfortunately there was you know
there was yeah there was there was guys
at certain events it was just it was
just standard and uh
yeah I think only the the majority of
the pros knew what was really going on
the fans didn't even know so it was
unless I'm wrong unless I'm naive now
you probably know best
well I find this fair I find this very
interesting and I want to kind of dig
deeper at this without you know really
saying names or anything
um
you said at least five players you don't
know exactly how many when do you think
it started like when when do you
remember this looking at the rack and
watching people do these things and be
like what is going on here to the point
where you actually looked into it and
found out what was happening
wow uh early early tens teens how do you
say that early teens
13 14.
maybe no it's got to be earlier than
that right but that's that's the naive
part where you didn't really know what
was going on yeah
ten eight eight nine ten twelve
for sure for sure I really started
seeing things at uh like 13 14.
uh and then it became kind of classic uh
at the Derby where it just started
seeing things that
weren't really possible like breaking
from the box and the corner balls flying
in 300 miles an hour straight on you
know stuff like that that doesn't happen
uh three times in a row that's
impossible
um
stuff like that I don't know I don't
want to make a big discussion out of it
but that's just what I what I saw and um
I think we've probably gone deep enough
on it but for me it's just a mission to
hear a top Pro actually refer to it as
cheating whereas it seems of universally
it's called rack manipulation rather
than just plainly cheating which is what
it actually is you know and the the
reason why I wanted to go is deep into
that as I did is because uh
well I'm bringing it back to that right
because one of the players that's that's
on the Hall of Fame and we talked about
this uh Mike pinozzo and uh Molina Mike
one of the reasons I won't allow court
or Corey duel won't get my vote was
because I think a lot of the stuff that
he did with the soft break and uh the
kind of manipulating of especially the
eight ball eight ball breaks where he
used to you know he I told the story of
uh when he was at the camera room in
Beloit at the spring classic he was
banking the wing ball off of an eight
ball rack making that ball and then
three balls would leave the rack but he
would make a ball so it's not an illegal
break and then he would just basically
Dink and dunk an entire rack and his
eight ball his eight ball racks would
take 15 to 20 minutes per piece because
he's playing safety breaks every single
time and I I don't know the exact start
to this but I've heard stories from
players that said basically the the
recommend uh manipulation was kind of
started by Corey dual off of that soft
break and the you know the kind of
things that went into that before
and I look at it as being cheating too I
mean I I look at absolutely if you're if
you're fingering the balls and you're
trying to get gaps in certain spots
you're trying to basically set you're
basically trying to take the the break
out of it you're saying you're no longer
playing a break you're playing a shot
and your shot is by hitting the racket
at this speed on this line and it's
going to make this ball here the the
break should not be a shot it should be
a break it should be a random explosion
of balls that you think you can try to
control uh but you don't always know
right well I think that we're happy with
these racks just interrupt your Nate I
think first of all I don't want to name
names that's for people to decide for
themselves
I just have an opinion about the wreck
but in the end of the day
it was up to the organizers to stop it
by putting in neutral records and when
that happened that solved the problem
right away now
having having said that I think there is
a skill into reading the wreck there's a
big skill in Reading rack that's that's
really knowledge uh if you can look at
Iraq and you can see certain things and
without manipulating you can see that
Ball's gone that that's a skill that's
knowledge
so I think not being allowed to look at
the rack uh I think that could go step
too far that's another discussion I
think that's a skill but manipulating a
rack of in my opinion goes too far
yeah I got no problem the people
checking Iraq if they want to decide
which side to break from if they think
one side's got a better advice than the
other but it's got to be 10 seconds it's
got to be 10 seconds or less though yeah
yeah yeah um but then I I think I think
the neutral record is absolutely
necessary for the future of pool and
unfortunately one of the one of the uh
the byproducts of that is I I believe I
remember a match that you had uh at the
whirlpool Masters this year if I'm not
mistaken I think it was hail Hill meals
and uh you smashed the rack and about
six balls uh got outside of the there's
like basically you smash the rack and
almost nothing opened up
I believe that was hill hill uh the
match that you lost uh
I mean this you know I mean we're
getting a little lost here but
um
the thing was there's always this
discussion right like okay you gotta
break and firm all right what is firm
what is firm
it's because there was uh
uh uh great layer uh great lady players
that joined the matchroom events the
previous years
on TV they broke as hard as they could
uh uh and then that was a kind of a
medium speed the the men player copied
that break and he gets a warning on TV
you have to break martyr so what is that
that's that's it doesn't work so that's
why they implemented the Three-Point
Rule now
that obviously doesn't work that well
for TV people get confused uh he made
two balls on a break but the other
players playing okay tough action but
what is firm you know we go to the the
break now I think the break as we have
it now is the best thing ever for nine
ball it's great if if balls are are
coming into the kitchen and I I felt uh
Carl Boyce said this really great on TV
at commentary you can see when a player
is putting his elbow in and he's making
an effort to hit these balls you can
tell right if he's doing this is not a
it's not an impactful break if you see
Guy uh accelerating he's putting in
speed
so I got a warning in my first match
you're soft breaking I said I said how
how can I be soft breaking it's a cut
break and you're not gonna see this big
break that you guys maybe want to see on
TV that's not the break that's working
with nine on the spot in a break box
so we had a uh an open discussion after
the match after the Joshua match
and we did some testing on TV I said
uh to sum it up if you hit the rack too
thin you're not going to get a lot of
action so you could have hit it with a
good speed but you hit him too thin so
you're losing impact or if you see all
these balls going to the side rail that
means the rack wasn't really Frozen so
that means you could also hit him pretty
good but now everything implodes to the
side wheel so I got a warning at both
instances and I went after the in the
timeout I said I'm not hitting these
balls off I'm hitting them as like I'm
I'm always doing so I get a warning I
had to make some adjustments it worked
out
and then against Kachi I got another
warning during the match I had to change
something and on hill hill I had to do
something different otherwise I would
lose the rack on a hill
so I broke I took a chance it didn't
work out and I lost the match but you
know
um I think I think still this break that
matchroom is doing is the the best break
with the template for for pro pool I
think it's the best best thing that I've
I've seen in the last 10 years for sure
but it just needs a little fine tuning
that's all
true
okay Jim you have any anything else that
Darren Appleton stops off breaking
I can't see he was online I got no clue
no Darren said he says he says you need
to stop soft breaking Paul
he doesn't have that power anymore Dan
you know how that feels yeah yeah Peter
Brown asked a good Bosnia story Niels
Bosnia story you got a good Bosnia story
Peter Brown no no I don't nah that's uh
I mean beautiful country
Boston has a beautiful country tough
history so it's uh
you have to go see for yourself but a
lot of nice friendly passionate people
uh
um really really no I'm happy to go back
to that tournaments like really good
passion so
one more one more thing
mosconi Cup this year you in you're
gonna get in this team
uh
uh my goal is to win a major
so the initial goal is not to get in the
Moscone cup because I'm not playing
enough events
uh but if I win that major I'm gonna be
right up there again so that's the way
if I'm gonna get in that's the way I'm
gonna get in not by racking up a lot and
a lot of points it's gonna have to be
one big bang I gotta make a big move
correct yeah
a couple of weeks yeah
unfortunately kachi's not going to be uh
looks like uh one of the Front Runners
for that
final what happened I saw a picture what
happened because I'm not on Facebook
he was racing he was racing and he
flipped his car had a massive car
accident and he smashed up his entire
arms engines are all torn broken tendon
Stone you could see he had the cast on
his and you could see his fingertips
were all black so there's obviously is a
lot of damage under there oh man oh wow
so he is a he's kind of I think he's
finished for the year I think probably
yeah
oh that sounds horrible but wait a
minute that puts me One More Time
by all accounts he was he was very lucky
to to walk out of it kind of thing yeah
yeah the message that I saw from him was
uh you know I'm I'm pretty messed up
that could have been a hell of a lot
worse so
yeah you know what he's like all these
cars and stuff like that it wouldn't
have been 30 miles an hour that he was
going kind of thing it would have uh
yeah I didn't know it was racing man all
right guys I'm gonna go back uh and put
the youngest
nielsenal took a little bit longer than
expected but listen thank you very much
delighted for you can't wait to see you
in filder it's your round
get practicing man congratulations
congratulations again all right cheers